<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Pandemic Preparedness Subprojects on The Swedish Pathogens Portal</title>
    <link>https://www.pathogens.se/resources-subprojects/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Pandemic Preparedness Subprojects on The Swedish Pathogens Portal</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><atom:link href="https://www.pathogens.se/resources-subprojects/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Highly parallelised multi-taxonomic profiling of shotgun metagenomic data (taxprofiler)</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/resources-subprojects/taxprofiler/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/resources-subprojects/taxprofiler/</guid>
      <description>A pipeline for taxonomic profiling of shotgun metagenomic data. It is currently in development and does not yet have any stable releases.
The pipeline supports metagenomic data generated both from Illumina and Nanopore sequencing technology. It performs in-parallel taxonomic profiling with multiple taxonomic classifiers against multiple databases and produces standardised output tables. In addition, it performs quality control and optional read pre-processing (adapter trimming, low-complexity filtering and host read removal).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>SARS-CoV-2 bioinformatics pipeline – GMS Arctic</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/resources-subprojects/gms-arctic/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/resources-subprojects/gms-arctic/</guid>
      <description>A pipeline for bioinformatical analysis of SARS-CoV-2 data was developed within Genomics Medicine Sweden during the spring of 2021. The pipeline extends on the analysis developed by the international collaboration ArticNetwork and the COG-UK consortium. It is currently in clinical use across Sweden and is continually updated with the latest SARS-CoV-2 variants.
The pipeline performs typing of SARS-CoV-2 data using both the Pangolin and Nextstrain classification systems. In addition, it also runs quality control, variant calling and supplies a genome consensus sequence for each sample.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>SARS-CoV-2 Reporter for visualization of SARS-CoV-2 genome sequence data (SC2reporter)</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/resources-subprojects/sc2reporter/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/resources-subprojects/sc2reporter/</guid>
      <description>A web-based visualization application for the ongoing SARS-CoV-2 pandemic. The tool is primarily used for epidemiological analysis where pipeline analysis results and metadata are loaded into a mongoDB database. The SNVs and indels can then be compared between all isolated in the database.
For more information on the Pandemic Laboratory Preparedness resources associated with this subproject, see Genomic Pandemic Preparedness Portfolio (G3P). Please also refer to other associated subprojects; GMS Arctic and taxprofiler.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>State-of-the-art biosafety level 3 (BSL3) facility</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/resources-subprojects/bsl3-facility/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/resources-subprojects/bsl3-facility/</guid>
      <description>BSL3 Biomedicum is fully equipped with state-of-the-art equipment and expertise staff to perform a wide range of research with any BSL3 pathogens. Our facility offers unique applications for pathogen aerobiology and high-throughput screening and service-based projects for external users.
BSL3 Biomedicum is open for companies to perform their research with pathogenic viruses. As an example, Biomedrex is developing CRISPR-based antivirals at BSL3 Biomedicum.
For more information on the Pandemic Laboratory Preparedness resources associated with this subproject, see BSL3 Biomedicum-SciLifeLab Collaborative Platform and Swedish biosafety level 3 (BSL3) network.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Swedish biosafety level 3 (BSL3) network</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/resources-subprojects/bsl3-network/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/resources-subprojects/bsl3-network/</guid>
      <description>High-level containment laboratories are a cornerstone for pandemic laboratory preparedness. The purpose of the Swedish BSL3 Network is to strengthen national pandemic laboratory preparedness by improving interactions between BSL3 facilities in the country.
For more information on the Pandemic Laboratory Preparedness resources associated with this subproject, see BSL3 Biomedicum-SciLifeLab Collaborative Platform and State-of-the-art biosafety level 3 (BSL3) facility.
Current members of the Swedish BSL3 network  </description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
