<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>The Swedish Pathogens Portal</title>
    <link>https://www.pathogens.se/</link>
    <description>Recent content on The Swedish Pathogens Portal</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 06 Nov 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.pathogens.se/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>ISIDORe offers services for infectious disease research</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/updates/isidore_services/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Nov 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/updates/isidore_services/</guid>
      <description>The ISIDORe project aims to accelerate research and enhance pandemic preparedness efforts across Europe by assembling and providing access to crucial research resources. This includes their state-of-the-art facilities, services, advanced equipment, and expertise.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New dashboard showing SARS-CoV-2 sequences in Uppsala</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/updates/clinmicro_dashboard_launch/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Nov 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/updates/clinmicro_dashboard_launch/</guid>
      <description>Today we are launching a new dashboard showing information on the SARS-CoV-2 sequences detected during surveillance efforts by the section for Clinical Microbiology and Hospital Hygiene at Uppsala University Hospital.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Influenza A(H5) virus: A potential pandemic threat</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/editorials/influenza/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/editorials/influenza/</guid>
      <description>A perspective on the potential for influenza viruses to be the next pandemic threat and how to be better prepared for the next pandemic.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Influenza added as a topic</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/updates/influenza_topic/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/updates/influenza_topic/</guid>
      <description>The content of the portal is broadly organised into &amp;lsquo;topics&amp;rsquo; related to pathogens and pandemic preparedness. Influenza is our latest topic.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New editorials section</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/updates/editorials/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/updates/editorials/</guid>
      <description>Today, we are launching a new section containing &amp;lsquo;editorials&amp;rsquo;. Editorials are short opinion-style articles detailing the &amp;lsquo;current thinking&amp;rsquo; on a given subject.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The pandemic has paved the way for data sharing</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/editorials/pandemic_data_sharing/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/editorials/pandemic_data_sharing/</guid>
      <description>Details the importance of sharing data, tools, and techniques in the COVID-19 pandemic and for future pandemic preparedness. Highlights how this applies to this year’s Nobel Prize in Medicine.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Large effort study to elucidate replication initiation in bacteria</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/highlights/bacterial_replication/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Sep 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/highlights/bacterial_replication/</guid>
      <description>This study by Knöppel, Broström et al is a large effort to elucidate replication initiation in bacteria. The authors have openly shared over 3 TB of microscopy imaging data.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Becoming the first national node of the Pathogens Portal</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/updates/pathogens_portal/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Aug 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/updates/pathogens_portal/</guid>
      <description>We are very proud to announce that we are transitioning the Portal into the first national node of the Pathogens Portal. This marks the next step in our efforts related to pandemic preparedness.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Update to include data on enteric viruses in wastewater</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/updates/wastewater_enteric_viruses/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Aug 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/updates/wastewater_enteric_viruses/</guid>
      <description>The Portal is happy to announce that the wastewater dashboard now includes data on the quantification of enteric viruses from the Norder group at Gothenburg University (GU).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Recent updates and upcoming improvements</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/updates/updates_june_23/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Jun 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/updates/updates_june_23/</guid>
      <description>An overview of recent updates and improvements, and things to look out for in future.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>METTL3 localisation during SARS-CoV-2 infection could highlight new novel antiviral strategy</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/highlights/mettl3_localisation/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 Jun 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/highlights/mettl3_localisation/</guid>
      <description>Vaid and Mendez, and collaborators, studied how the gene expression profile of m6A mRNA is affected both during and after COVID-19 infection. All sequencing data and the source code for analysis are shared.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>National COVID-19 biobank sample collection made available for research on the Portal</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/updates/npc_national_collection/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/updates/npc_national_collection/</guid>
      <description>A unique new sample collection has been added to the COVID-19 Sample Collection Database. The collection comprises of over 1.5 million samples collected by Swedish healthcare regions and processed by the National Pandemic Centre throughout the COVID-19 pandemic.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Variability in IGH antibody genes influences the response to SARS-CoV-2</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/highlights/igh_antibody_genes/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/highlights/igh_antibody_genes/</guid>
      <description>Pushparaj and colleagues use genotyping and haplotype analysis to show high genetic diversity in IGH genes among humans, which may influence our response to infections. Data, and IgDiscover software shared.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Swedish national resources on IDTk</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/updates/idtk_nation_resource/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/updates/idtk_nation_resource/</guid>
      <description>The Portal is a partner in the BY-COVID project. We have added a page to the Infectious Diseases Toolkit (IDTk) related to infectious disease data in Sweden.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Update to wastewater epidemiology dashboard</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/updates/update_wastewater_section/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/updates/update_wastewater_section/</guid>
      <description>The Portal team is working closely with groups at multiple Swedish universities that are involved in wastewater epidemiology to bring you the latest research in this area.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New study shows that perserverance can be the reason for antibiotic resistance development</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/highlights/antibiotic_resistance_development/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/highlights/antibiotic_resistance_development/</guid>
      <description>A study from Elf lab at Uppsala University/SciLifeLab shows perseverance can be a reason for antibiotic resistance development in &lt;em&gt;E. coli&lt;/em&gt;. Microscopy image data shared in SciLifeLab Data Repository.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New section for pandemic preparedness events</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/updates/events_section/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/updates/events_section/</guid>
      <description>A new section has been added to promote events relevant to pandemic preparedness. This could include, for example, events related to biobanks, antibiotic resistance, or particular pathogens.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Portal welcomes editorial committee</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/updates/editorial_committee_23/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/updates/editorial_committee_23/</guid>
      <description>An editorial committee has now been established. The members will work closely with us to maximise the value of the Portal for the research community.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dashboard on Register-based COVID-19 Vaccination Study (RECOVAC) updated &amp; expanded</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/updates/recovac_update/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/updates/recovac_update/</guid>
      <description>New information related to determinants of vaccination and vaccine effectiveness have been added to the RECOVAC dashboard. The data has also been updated.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cryo-electron tomography allows new knowledge about poliovirus replication and assembly sites in situ</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/highlights/poliovirus_replication/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/highlights/poliovirus_replication/</guid>
      <description>Dahmane et al (2022) used Cryo-electron tomography to provide an integrated structural framework for multiple stages of the poliovirus life cycle. Data and code are shared openly.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Explore COVID-19 publications in the field of social sciences and humanities on the Portal</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/updates/social_science_launch/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/updates/social_science_launch/</guid>
      <description>The Portal contains a database of COVID-19 publications involving Swedish researchers, and an available data section that shows which share data and/or code. It has long been possible to filter both the database and available databases by certain topics. Now, it is possible to identify the research, data, and code related to social sciences and humanities.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A wider variety of data sources contribute to better spatio-temporal predictions of COVID-19 test positivity</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/highlights/covidtest_spatiotemp_uppsala/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/highlights/covidtest_spatiotemp_uppsala/</guid>
      <description>Van Zoest &lt;em&gt;et al&lt;/em&gt; (2022) developed and evaluated the performance of four different statistical single models and one ensemble model to predict trends in COVID-19 test positivity. Data are shared openly in GitHub.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Data-driven research shows that Neanderthal gene connected to severity of COVID-19 (Update)</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/highlights/neanderthal_gene_data_driven/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/highlights/neanderthal_gene_data_driven/</guid>
      <description>Study by Hugo Zeberg and Svante Pääbo fully based on openly available data published open access in &lt;em&gt;Nature&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Now a Nobel Prize winner!!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The latest updates to the COVID-19 &amp; Pandemic Preparedness Portal</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/updates/new_look/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/updates/new_look/</guid>
      <description>The scope of the portal has expanded in 2022 to include other pathogens and pandemic preparedness in general. We&amp;rsquo;ve created lots of new content and features in response to this (with more planned!).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Relaunch as Swedish COVID-19 and Pandemic Preparedness Portal</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/updates/pandemic_preparedness_transition/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/updates/pandemic_preparedness_transition/</guid>
      <description>Today we officially relaunch the site as the Swedish COVID-19 and Pandemic Preparedness Portal. We have been gradually transitioning sections of the Portal throughout 2022. Our latest section involves a collation of resources related to pandemic preparedness.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Direct RT-PCR used to monitor Omicron BA.1/BA.2 variant transition in Sweden (Update)</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/highlights/omicron_variant_transition/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/highlights/omicron_variant_transition/</guid>
      <description>Lentini and collegues used direct RT-PCR to show the transition from Omicron BA.1 to sub-variant BA.2 in Sweden Jan-March 2022. New Preprint from Reinius lab which shares data and code.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Section on Register-based COVID-19 Vaccination Study (RECOVAC) launched</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/updates/recovac/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/updates/recovac/</guid>
      <description>Data visualisations, information, and publications related to the RECOVAC project are now available on the portal. Visualisation codes are publicly available.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Swedish COVID-19 Data Portal two year anniversary</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/updates/second_year/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/updates/second_year/</guid>
      <description>The national Swedish COVID-19 Data Portal was launched two years ago today. The portal has been an important part of the pandemic response in Sweden. On our anniversary, we reflect on past highlights and look to the future.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Study of host-viral interactions of Crimean-Congo haemorrhagic fever identified potential new drugs</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/highlights/crimean_congo_interactions/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/highlights/crimean_congo_interactions/</guid>
      <description>New study gives insight into host-viral interactions of Crimean-Congo hemorrhagic fever, an infectious disease without available treatments. Raw RNAseq, mass spectrometry proteomics data and code shared.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Large scale immunofluorescence to explore the host cell response to SARS-CoV-2 infection</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/highlights/immunofluorescence/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/highlights/immunofluorescence/</guid>
      <description>Expression of 602 host proteins were evaluated in populations of infected and non-infected cells using immunofluorescence. ≈75,000 images have been published as a resource for further studies.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Interactions between fragments and SARS-CoV-2 nsp10 provide insight into the viral replications</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/highlights/fragments_nsp10/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/highlights/fragments_nsp10/</guid>
      <description>Interactions between fragments and SARS-CoV-2 nsp10 have been successfully identified and characterised by Kozielski and colleagues. Data shared on the Protein Data Bank and Zenodo.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Study provides important insights for future predictions of SARS CoV-2 infection</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/highlights/sars-cov2_t-cell_response/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/highlights/sars-cov2_t-cell_response/</guid>
      <description>Mangsbo and colleagues investigated sensitivity and specificity of a SARS-CoV-2 T-cell assay. Research warrants further research into that future T-cell receptor sequencing as future tools for prediction of previous infections.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Newly discovered Fu2 nanobody hold potential for future antiviral development</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/highlights/bispecific_monomeric_nanobody/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/highlights/bispecific_monomeric_nanobody/</guid>
      <description>In this study, Hanke and colleagues discovered a new nanobody. The new RBD-specific Fu2 nanobody was found to utilize a unique neutralization mechanism. Data was shared openly in, eg. The Electron Microscopy Data Bank.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tutorial for SARS-CoV-2 genome data submission to ENA now available</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/updates/ena_tutorial/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/updates/ena_tutorial/</guid>
      <description>Today, we are launching a ENA tutorial on how to submit SARS-CoV2 sequences to the European Nucleotide Archive. The tutorial caters to both experienced and first time sequence submitters.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>OAS1 splicing found to be associated with risk of severe COVID-19</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/highlights/oas1_splicing_and_severe_covid/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/highlights/oas1_splicing_and_severe_covid/</guid>
      <description>In this article, Huffman et al studied individuals across different ancestry groups and discusses the association between OAS1 splicing and severity of COVID-19. Data related to this study is shared publicly.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mass spectrometry suggested as a future essential analytical contribution to Covid-19 pandemic readiness</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/highlights/massspec_pandemic_prep/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/highlights/massspec_pandemic_prep/</guid>
      <description>Hober et al. present how LC-MRM/MS could form the basis of a scalable method that should facilitate future pandemic preparedness. The data has been openly shared.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Statistics, information, and research related to COVID-19 Vaccination in Sweden now available on the Portal</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/updates/vaccines_page/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/updates/vaccines_page/</guid>
      <description>The Visualizations are based on data freely available from the Swedish Health Agency (Folkhälsomyndigheten).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Host factor interaction between human G3BP proteins and SARS-CoV-2 N-protein could represent an antiviral target</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/highlights/g3bp_antivirual_target/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/highlights/g3bp_antivirual_target/</guid>
      <description>Kruse and Benz et al. describe a scalable method of investigating virus-host interactions that can be used as a means of identifying potential targets for novel antiviral drugs. All data from the study have been shared publicly.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Drug repurposing identifies Fostamatinib as a drug with potentially high efficacy in COVID-19 treatment</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/highlights/drug_repurposing/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/highlights/drug_repurposing/</guid>
      <description>Recent study finds that drug repurposing can offer an average of an 11-fold increase in disease coverage and demonstrates its value for COVID-19. All data and code that support the findings have been made publicly available.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>BY-COVID – a collaborative effort to tackle data challenges that can hinder effective pandemic response</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/updates/by-covid/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/updates/by-covid/</guid>
      <description>The BeYond-COVID (BY-COVID) is a recently launched €12 million project funded by Horizon Europe. The Swedish COVID-19 Data Portal is one of the 53 partners from 19 countries taking part in the project.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New section on the Portal about register-based research</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/updates/section_register_based_research/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/updates/section_register_based_research/</guid>
      <description>The Swedish COVID-19 Data Portal is launching &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.pathogens.se/data_types/health_data/register_based_research/&#34;&gt;a section on register-based research in Sweden&lt;/a&gt; containing an overview of relevant registers and examples of research projects have used register data.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Clues to the genetic factors underlying greater susceptibility to severe COVID-19 in men</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/highlights/x_linked_genes/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/highlights/x_linked_genes/</guid>
      <description>The COVID Human Genetic Efforts consortium published a study on genetic factors underlying greater susceptibility to the severe COVID-19 in men. Relevant RNA-seq data were shared in Gene Expression Omnibus (GEO).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reliable profiling of IgG and IgM levels in home-sampled dried blood spots</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/highlights/serology_in_home_sampled_dbs/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/highlights/serology_in_home_sampled_dbs/</guid>
      <description>Roxhed et al. demonstrate how self sampling at home can be effective by profiling IgG and IgM levels against several versions of SARS-CoV-2 proteins (S, RBD, N) in home-sampled dried blood spots. Metadata records and the analysis scripts used in the study are shared.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Metabolic perturbation of SARS-CoV-2 as a potential future therapeutic target</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/highlights/metabolic_perturbation_therapeutic_target/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/highlights/metabolic_perturbation_therapeutic_target/</guid>
      <description>Krishnan et al. showed that the SARS-CoV-2 virus can use and rewire metabolic pathways to their benefit in replication. Their findings indicate that host metabolic perturbation could be an attractive strategy to limit replication. Code and data from the study have been shared pubicly.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Statistics, information, and research about Post COVID-19 condition in Sweden now available on the Portal</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/updates/postcovid_launch/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/updates/postcovid_launch/</guid>
      <description>Today, for the first time, the Portal provides information and summary statistics to show the impact of ‘Post COVID-19 condition’ (‘Postcovid’ in Swedish) in Sweden, and the research underway. All data and code used on the page is publicly available.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Human genetic mapping can provide insight about COVID-19 pathogenesis and drug development</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/highlights/insights_from_genetic_mapping/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/highlights/insights_from_genetic_mapping/</guid>
      <description>Researchers in the COVID-19 Host Genetics initiative performed genome-wide association meta-analyses to examine the loci involved in the variation of COVID-19 disease severity and susceptibility between individuals. The data and code used in the project have been made available.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New phenomics method for antiviral drug discovery may help to fight COVID-19</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/highlights/phenomics_method_drug_discovery/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/highlights/phenomics_method_drug_discovery/</guid>
      <description>Rietdijk and colleagues used a new phenomics approach to aid in the discovery of both novel drugs and drugs that could potentially be repurposed to fight COVID-19. Both data and code are published.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Interferon signatures in SARS-CoV-2 infected liver cells could provide knowledge for new antiviral therapies</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/highlights/interferon_signatures_liver/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/highlights/interferon_signatures_liver/</guid>
      <description>Chen and Saccon et al. used a proteomics-based approach to study how SARS-CoV-2 infection affected Type-1 interferon signalling in liver cells. Both data and code are published.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cost-effective COVseq method could be used for large-scale genomic surveillance of VOCs</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/highlights/covseq_surveillance_vocs/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/highlights/covseq_surveillance_vocs/</guid>
      <description>Simonetti, Zhang, and Harbers et al. have shared a cost-effective, scalable and versatile method (alongside associated data and code) that could facilitate large-scale genomic surveillance of variants of concern (VOCs).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Swedish SARS-CoV-2 and COVID-19 research output since the beginning of the pandemic</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/updates/covid_publications/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/updates/covid_publications/</guid>
      <description>To date, 1.400+ journal articles and preprints have been published by researchers affiliated to a Swedish university or research institute. The database of these publications is compiled by the Portal and is available for download.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Swedish COVID-19 Data Portal one year on - focus on openly sharing data and code</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/updates/first_year/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/updates/first_year/</guid>
      <description>One year ago today, on June 3rd 2020, the Swedish COVID-19 Data Portal was launched and became the first national node of the European data sharing platform for COVID-19 research efforts. Here, we look back at the highlights over the last year.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Quantitative proteomic provides important knowledge about cellular response against SARS CoV-2</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/highlights/cellular_response/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/highlights/cellular_response/</guid>
      <description>Saccon and colleagues studied changes in protein abundance caused by SARS-CoV-2 virus in susceptible cell lines using quantitative proteomics. All proteomics were made data openly available in different repositories.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Proteomic profiling in COVID-19 patients as biomarkers to monitor disease severity</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/highlights/proteomic_blood_profiling/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/highlights/proteomic_blood_profiling/</guid>
      <description>Recent study examined a large number of inflammatory, immune response, cardiovascular, and neurological markers in the blood of patients variously impacted by COVID-19. Data and analysis code were shared in public repositories.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Swedish COVID-19 symptom data contribute to accelerating research about pandemic</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/highlights/symptom-study-sweden/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/highlights/symptom-study-sweden/</guid>
      <description>COVID Symptom Study Sweden collects data through a smartphone app to investigate prevalence, risk factors, and symptoms associated with COVID-19. To date, over 200.000 volunteers have enrolled in the study.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>SARS-CoV-2 wastewater data from cities across Sweden now available</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/updates/wastewater-data/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/updates/wastewater-data/</guid>
      <description>The Swedish COVID-19 Data Portal is launching &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.pathogens.se/data_types/environment/wastewater/&#34;&gt;a section with wastewater epidemiology data&lt;/a&gt;. Weekly data from Uppsala, Stockholm, Umeå, and Örebro is presented in graphs and available for download.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Neanderthal gene protecting against severe COVID-19 could be potential new drug target</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/highlights/neanderthal-gene-protecting/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/highlights/neanderthal-gene-protecting/</guid>
      <description>A new study largely relying on existing data re-use identified circulating proteins influencing COVID-19 susceptibility and severity. Based on these results, work on repurposing relevant existing drugs work can now be launched.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Database of COVID-19 sample collections and biobanks in Sweden launched</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/updates/sample_collection_database/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/updates/sample_collection_database/</guid>
      <description>In collaboration with Biobank Sweden, today we are launching a new section of the portal: the &lt;a href=&#34;https://biobanks.covid19dataportal.se/&#34;&gt;Swedish COVID-19 Sample Collection Database&lt;/a&gt;. The database allows to search for available biobank sample collections.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bevacizumab treatment beneficial for patients with severe COVID-19</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/highlights/bevacizumab_treatment/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/highlights/bevacizumab_treatment/</guid>
      <description>A recently published clinical study investigating bevacizumab, a humanized anti-VEGF monoclonal antibody, offers promising results in fighting severe COVID-19. Treatment progress data and analysis code were shared publicly.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Nanobodies promising new therapeutics for treatment of SARS CoV-2</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/highlights/nanobodies_treatment/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/highlights/nanobodies_treatment/</guid>
      <description>A recently published study characterizes the mechanisms by which nanobodies neutralize or prevent of infection in molecular detail. Crystallographic coordinates, cryo-EM density maps, and atomic coordinates were deposited to public databases.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Data on COVID-19 testing in Uppsala County and dashboard with maps, trends and more now available</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/updates/crush_covid/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/updates/crush_covid/</guid>
      <description>The data portal is now launching &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.pathogens.se/data_types/health_data/crush_covid/&#34;&gt;a page with the CRUSH Covid dashboard&lt;/a&gt; with an option to download data on COVID-19 testing in each postal code of Uppsala County.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mechanism of entry used by human species D adenoviruses proving important for COVID-19 vaccine development</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/highlights/adenovirus/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/highlights/adenovirus/</guid>
      <description>New study identifies a noncanonical entry mechanism used by human adenoviruses, important for development of adenovirus-based vaccine vectors. The reported X-ray structural data was made available through the Protein Data Bank.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A novel approach to discover and characterize broad-spectrum antivirals</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/highlights/antivirals/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/highlights/antivirals/</guid>
      <description>Newly discovered antiviral compounds showed broad-range antiviral activity against pathogenic RNA viruses such as SARS-CoV-2. The authors share data freely in open repositories.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Pathogenesis of hyperinflammatory syndrome associated with COVID-19 in children</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/highlights/multisystem_inflammatory_syndrome/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/highlights/multisystem_inflammatory_syndrome/</guid>
      <description>Multiple autoantibodies and specific cytokines could be involved in the pathogenesis of MIS-C associated with COVID-19. Data and code made available in open repositories.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>An alpaca-derived nanobody can potently neutralize SARS-CoV-2</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/highlights/alpaca-nanobody/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/highlights/alpaca-nanobody/</guid>
      <description>Leo Hanke and colleagues identified a SARS-CoV-2 RBD-specific single domain antibody fragment, &lt;em&gt;Ty1&lt;/em&gt;, that potently neutralizes the virus. Ty1 should now be further investigated as a candidate for antiviral therapy.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Synthetic nanobodies are easy to produce and can effectively neutralize SARS-CoV-2</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/highlights/synthetic_nanobodies/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/highlights/synthetic_nanobodies/</guid>
      <description>Recently published study demonstrates that it is possible to select highly specific binders with neutralizing activity against SARS-CoV-2 from a synthetic nanobody library in a short timeframe.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>MAIT cell activation and dynamics studied in relation to COVID-19 disease severity</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/highlights/immunopathogenesis/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/highlights/immunopathogenesis/</guid>
      <description>Tiphaine Parrot and colleagues studied changes in conventional and unconventional T cell subsets in patients with various disease severity using flow cytometry. The results were published along with the data.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Crystal structure of SARS CoV-2 nsp-10 - a potential drug target for COVID-19</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/highlights/nsp10_crystal_structure/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/highlights/nsp10_crystal_structure/</guid>
      <description>A study by Rogstam and colleagues published along with the crystal structure of SARS CoV-2 non-structural protein 10 in the Protein Data Bank provides a starting point for structure-guided drug discovery and design.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bayesian model for estimating the impact of mobility patterns on COVID-19 infection</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/highlights/estimating_impact_mobility_patterns/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/highlights/estimating_impact_mobility_patterns/</guid>
      <description>Patrick Bryant and Arne Elofsson shared code and instructions for modelling COVID-19 development using MCMC simulations based on mobile phone mobility data from Google mobility reports.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>First study using data collected as part of the large-scale serology testing at SciLifeLab published</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/highlights/serological_investigation_collaborations/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/highlights/serological_investigation_collaborations/</guid>
      <description>This study used only a fraction of the large volume of serology data continuously collected by the ScilifeLab Autoimmunity and Serology profiling facility.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Method circumventing RNA extraction in RT-PCR COVID-19 testing published along with data</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/highlights/rna_extraction_free_rt_pcr/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/highlights/rna_extraction_free_rt_pcr/</guid>
      <description>Study by Björn Reinius and co-workers published open access in &lt;em&gt;Nature Communications&lt;/em&gt; along with source data and the computational code.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Statistics on SARS-CoV-2 antibody tests carried out by SciLifeLab now available</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/updates/serology_testing_stats/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/updates/serology_testing_stats/</guid>
      <description>We are launching a page with statistics on the SARS-CoV-2 antibody tests carried out at the SciLifeLab Autoimmunity and Serology profiling facility.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Add a new biobank to the Swedish COVID-19 Sample Collection database</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/biobanks/add_biobank/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/biobanks/add_biobank/</guid>
      <description>The form below can be used to add a new biobank to the Swedish COVID-19 Sample Collection database which is part of the Swedish national COVID-19 data portal. All information provided in the form below will be displayed on the page of the biobank in the registry. Please fill in as many fields as possible so that the researchers have a good idea about what they can expect from the biobank.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Add a new collection to the Swedish COVID-19 Sample Collection database</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/biobanks/add_collection/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/biobanks/add_collection/</guid>
      <description>The form below can be used to add a new collection to the Swedish COVID-19 Sample Collection database which is part of the Swedish national COVID-19 data portal. All information provided in the form below will be displayed on the page of the collection in the registry. Please fill in as many fields as possible so that the researchers have a good idea about what they can expect from the collection.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>All data types</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/datasets/all/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/datasets/all/</guid>
      <description>Published Data </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Amount of SARS-CoV-2 in wastewater (GU)</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/dashboards/wastewater/covid_quantification/covid_quant_gu/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/dashboards/wastewater/covid_quantification/covid_quant_gu/</guid>
      <description>Go back to SARS-CoV-2 quantification within the wastewater epidemiology dashboard  Introduction This project is led by Professor Helene Norder (University of Gothenburg, GU), and supported by co-workers from the University of Gothenburg and Sahlgrenska University Hospital (Hao Wang, Marianela Patzi Churqui, Timur Tunovic, Fredy Saguti, and Kristina Nyström). The wastewater sample collections were performed by Lucica Enache at Ryaverket, Gryaab AB, Gothenburg.
The data and visualisation on this page are usually updated weekly.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Amount of SARS-CoV-2 in wastewater (SEEC-KTH)</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/dashboards/wastewater/covid_quantification/covid_quant_kth/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/dashboards/wastewater/covid_quantification/covid_quant_kth/</guid>
      <description>As of June 2023, the SARS-CoV-2 data will no longer be updated by SEEC-KTH. Data from after June 2023 is available from other research groups.  Go back to SARS-CoV-2 quantification within the wastewater epidemiology dashboard  Introduction This project is led by associate professor Zeynep Cetecioglu Gurol and supported by Mariel Perez-Zabaleta and Isaac Owusu-Agyeman at KTH Royal Institute of Technology (KTH). Bioinformatics analyses of wastewater samples are held by assistant professor Luisa Hugerth (Uppsala University).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Amount of SARS-CoV-2 in wastewater (SEEC-SLU)</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/dashboards/wastewater/covid_quantification/covid_quant_slu/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/dashboards/wastewater/covid_quantification/covid_quant_slu/</guid>
      <description>Go back to SARS-CoV-2 quantification within the wastewater epidemiology dashboard  Introduction Severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS‑CoV‑2) is a positive-sense single-stranded RNA virus that causes COVID-19 (coronavirus disease 2019), the respiratory illness responsible for the COVID-19 pandemic. SARS-CoV-2 was first identified in the city of Wuhan, Hubei, China, and the World Health Organization (WHO) declared a public health emergency of international concern from January 30, 2020, to May 5, 2023.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Antibiotic resistance</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/topics/antibiotic-resistance/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/topics/antibiotic-resistance/</guid>
      <description>Antibiotic resistance is a new topic on the Portal, and we are currently working on adding more information.  Background COVID-19 has been the focus of people across the world during the last two years of the current pandemic. Antibiotic resistance, by contrast, has been termed a &amp;lsquo;silent pandemic&amp;rsquo; because whilst, like COVID-19, it is widespread and poses a real and present danger to public health, it is receiving relatively little attention.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Biochemistry data</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/datasets/biochemistry/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/datasets/biochemistry/</guid>
      <description>Published Data On our portal, “Biochemistry” has a broad meaning, including cell- and plasma profiling with, for example, biomarker concentrations in plasma.
General useful data sources   Small molecule related data can be found in ChEMBL. ChEMBL is a manually curated database of bioactive molecules with drug-like properties. It brings together chemical, bioactivity and genomic data to aid the translation of genomic information into effective new drugs.
  IntAct Molecular Interaction Database - a freely available, open source database system and analysis tools for molecular interaction data.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Browser-based tools and AI models</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/ai_models_tools/examples_internal/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/ai_models_tools/examples_internal/</guid>
      <description> ITK/VTK Viewer To visualize an image with ITK/VTK viewer, click here
Vizarr Vizarr is a client-side program for viewing Zarr-based images with Viv &amp;amp; ImJoy
Vizarr be embedded in the page directly:
 You can also view the image in a dialog by clicking here Kaibu Example To annotate an image with Kaibu, click here
Other Applications HPA UMAP: run
 HPA Classification: run
 </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>BSL3 Biomedicum-SciLifeLab Collaborative Platform</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/resources/bsl3/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/resources/bsl3/</guid>
      <description>This resource involves two separate components:
1. Swedish biosafety level 3 (BSL3) network For more information on the BSL3 network (including information on access, use, and contact), please see the dedicated BSL3 network page.
Current members of the Swedish BSL3 network  2. State-of-the-art biosafety level 3 (BSL3) facility For more information on the BSL3 facility (including information on access, use, and contact), please see the dedicated BSL3 facility page.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Children with acute hepatitis of unknown etiology</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/pathogens/hepatitis_unknown_origin/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/pathogens/hepatitis_unknown_origin/</guid>
      <description>Background Hepatitis (severe liver inflammation) can result from pathogens, toxins, or autoimmune reactions. Most often, it is caused by the hepatitis A, B, D, or E viruses (hepatitis D is always found together with B). However, other viruses, such as the Epstein-Barr virus or Cytomegalovirus (CMV), may cause hepatitis in children.
Patients often exhibit a yellowish colouration in the skin and whites of the eye, as well as gastrointestinal symptoms, such as vomiting, diarrhea, and light faeces.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Contribute</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/contribute/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/contribute/</guid>
      <description>The Swedish Pathogens Portal was built to serve the community of researchers working on relevant topics and we welcome any contributions from the community or suggestions on how the Portal can help the community. Whenever there is anything that you would like to share with your colleagues, do not hesistate to share it through the Portal. We welcome suggestions for new information or edits in all sections as well as ideas for new sections that could be launched.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>COVID Symptom Study Sweden</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/dashboards/symptom_study_sweden/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/dashboards/symptom_study_sweden/</guid>
      <description>COVID Symptom Study Sweden is a national research initiative for large-scale data collection and analysis of symptoms, exposure, and risk factors associated with the COVID-19 infection. The project is run by Lund University and Uppsala University in collaboration with King’s College London and Zoe Global Ltd. COVID Symptom Study Sweden is led by prof. Paul Franks and prof. Maria Gomez (Lund University) as well as prof. Tove Fall (Uppsala University).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>COVID-19</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/topics/covid-19/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/topics/covid-19/</guid>
      <description>Background Coronavirus disease (COVID-19) is an infectious disease caused by the novel SARS-CoV-2 virus. Since its start in early 2020, the COVID-19 pandemic has challenged societies worldwide. While most people infected experience mild to moderate respiratory illness and recover without treatment, the disease can be severe or fatal. Advanced age and underlying medical conditions, such as cardiovascular disease, diabetes, cancer, or chronic respiratory disease, have all been associated with increased risk of severe outcome.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>CRUSH Covid data and dashboard, Region Uppsala</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/dashboards/crush_covid/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/dashboards/crush_covid/</guid>
      <description>CRUSH Covid Uppsala is a research project in which Region Uppsala collaborates with researchers from five different research departments at Uppsala University. The purpose of the project is to map outbreaks of COVID-19 in Uppsala County and to try to mitigate the impact of outbreaks by informing the public.
CRUSH Covid is led by Mats Martinell (senior lecturer at the Department of Public Health and Caring Sciences, General Medicine and Preventive Medicine, Uppsala University) and Tove Fall (professor of Molecular Epidemiology at the Department of Medical Sciences, Molecular Epidemiology, Uppsala University).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Data management</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/data-management/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/data-management/</guid>
      <description>&amp;ldquo;Research data management concerns the organization, storage, preservation, and sharing of data that is collected or analysed during a research project. Proper planning and management of research data will make project management easier and more efficient while projects are being performed. It also facilitates sharing and allows others to validate as well as reuse the data. Also, funding agencies are recognizing the importance of research data management and some now request Data Management Plans (DMP) as part of the grant application process.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Development of a targeted metagenomic NGS platform for diagnostics and epidemiological surveillance of viral pandemic threats</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/resources/ngs_surveillance/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/resources/ngs_surveillance/</guid>
      <description>The aim of this project is to develop and implement a targeted metagenomic next-generation sequencing-based (mNGS) platform that utilizes a hybrid-capture and amplification approach for sensitive and accurate detection of viral pathogens. The focus will be on an enrichment panel that can detect &amp;gt; 3,000 viral species.
Project outline
The proposed system includes implementation of validated methods for:
 Constructing Illumina TruSeq sequencing libraries Performing target-capture using Twist BioScience oligomer panels Performing post-capture library amplification Sequencing on Illumina instruments (MiniSeq, MiSeq, NextSeq) Automated, reproducible bioinformatics workflow (NextFlow) Data storage and management User-friendly presentation of results (secure web application, LDAP/AD user authentication, database backend) Submission of data generated as part of consented academic studies to the ScliLifeLabs Data Centre in adherence with open science standards (FAIR)  Project development</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Drug discovery data</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/datasets/drug-discovery/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/datasets/drug-discovery/</guid>
      <description>Published Data </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Editorial committee</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/about/editorial_committee/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/about/editorial_committee/</guid>
      <description>Below are the six editorial committee members for 2023, alongside their affiliation and area of expertise. The editorial committee enable a more direct link between the Portal and the wider research community. They collaborate with the Portal team to create content and advise on resources that would be beneficial to researchers in their area of expertise.
  Ben Murrell, PhD   Karolinska Institute   Expertise: Computational biology,</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Enteric viruses</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/topics/enteric-viruses/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/topics/enteric-viruses/</guid>
      <description>Background Enteric viruses are viruses that are primarily transmitted via the faecal-oral route, and that cause enteric disease (with symptoms e.g. nausea, diarrhea, vomiting, and abdominal pain). Many families of viruses are enteric viruses, including, for example, calicivirus (including norovirus and sapovirus), adenoviruses, astroviruses, rotaviruses, hepatitis viruses, and enteroviruses. Most enteric viruses cause only relatively mild symptoms in healthy individuals, some enteric viruses (e.g. poliovirus) can have serious health effect, with symptoms including meningitis and paralysis.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Establishing sequencing-based viral diagnostics for future clinical use: towards pandemic and outbreak preparedness in the clinical laboratory</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/resources/seq_based_diagnostics/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/resources/seq_based_diagnostics/</guid>
      <description>This proposal builds on the collaboration between the Dept. of Clinical Microbiology at Region Skåne, the Dept. of Translational Medicine, Section of Clinical Virology at Lund University, and Clinical Ge- nomics Lund at SciLifeLab, to develop and disseminate new state-of-the-art viral diagnostics meth- ods for improved Swedish healthcare. This collaboration already successfully established and im- plemented whole-genome sequencing (WGS) of SARS-CoV-2 during the pandemic (since February 2021).
WGS of pathogens is becoming increasingly important for clinical science and practice.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Genomic Pandemic Preparedness Portfolio (G3P) – Nationally scalable genomics portfolio for detection and surveillance of viral outbreaks</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/resources/g3p/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/resources/g3p/</guid>
      <description>The current SARS-CoV-2 pandemic highlights the need of building pandemic preparedness capabilities for genetic monitoring (surveillance) of pathogens causing pandemics, as well as early detection of emerging pathogens and antimicrobial resistance in future pandemics and outbreaks. Therefore, our project focus on sequencing-based pandemic preparedness, by developing laboratory assays, along with associated bioinformatics analysis workflows, data visualisation for knowledge sharing and interpretation, and other tools for efficient national coverage.
Developed assays and tools will be established across the SciLifeLab´s Clinical Genomics nodes, Genomic Medicine Centers, and clinical microbiology laboratories to reach national coverage, minimise the distance to point-of-care, and ensuring rapid turnaround times.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Genomics &amp; transcriptomics data</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/datasets/genomics-transcriptomics/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/datasets/genomics-transcriptomics/</guid>
      <description>Published Data Data available on the European COVID-19 Data Portal Published raw and assembled sequences related to the COVID-19 outbreak, including outbreak isolates and records relating to coronavirus biology:
 Raw and assembled sequence and analysis of SARS-CoV-2 and other coronaviruses (&amp;gt;500,000 deposited items as of June 2021) Raw and assembled sequence and analysis of human and other hosts (&amp;gt;15,000 deposited items as of June 2021) European Genome-phenome Archive (EGA) - service for permanent archiving and sharing of all types of personally identifiable genetic and phenotypic data resulting from biomedical research projects.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Get support</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/support/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/support/</guid>
      <description>Below is an overview of relevant support services (free or against a fee) provided by the research infrastructures in Sweden that is available for research projects related to pandemic preparedness.
 Support on using the Portal If you have questions or suggestions for the Swedish Pathogens Portal, you can get in touch with the Portal team either by filling out our contact form or by sending an email to datacentre@scilifelab.se.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Gothenburg initiative for pandemic laboratory preparedness (GILP)</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/resources/glip/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/resources/glip/</guid>
      <description>Clinical Microbiology, Sahlgrenska University Hospital (CMSU) is one of the largest microbiology laboratories in northern Europe. It provides microbiological diagnostics to a population of 1.2 million people and collaborates with the Institute of Biomedicine, University of Gothenburg, on a broad range of research projects, including several on Covid-19. During the Covid-19 pandemic CMSU was the first hospital laboratory in Sweden to offer SARS-CoV-2 RNA testing and the first to provide test results on mobile phones.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Health data</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/datasets/health/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/datasets/health/</guid>
      <description>Published Data Data available from Swedish public agencies and large data produces   Public Health Agency of Sweden:
 Number of cases and tests: Official statistics about COVID-19 cases and tests in Sweden. Number of administered vaccine doses: Official statistics about the number of vaccines that have been administered in Sweden. Variants of concern: Official variants of concern in Sweden.    Swedish National Board of Health and Welfare (Socialstyrelsen): Statistics on COVID-19 in Sweden - underlying cause of death; infected and deceased among the elderly and among persons with disabilities and residential arrangements; inpatient care (updated every Wednesday).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Highly parallelised multi-taxonomic profiling of shotgun metagenomic data (taxprofiler)</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/resources-subprojects/taxprofiler/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/resources-subprojects/taxprofiler/</guid>
      <description>A pipeline for taxonomic profiling of shotgun metagenomic data. It is currently in development and does not yet have any stable releases.
The pipeline supports metagenomic data generated both from Illumina and Nanopore sequencing technology. It performs in-parallel taxonomic profiling with multiple taxonomic classifiers against multiple databases and produces standardised output tables. In addition, it performs quality control and optional read pre-processing (adapter trimming, low-complexity filtering and host read removal).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Historic data for Stockholm</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/dashboards/wastewater/covid_quantification/historic_stockholm/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/dashboards/wastewater/covid_quantification/historic_stockholm/</guid>
      <description>This page displays data on the amount of SARS-CoV-2 in Stockholm between April 2020 and August 2021 calculated as Gene copy number/week (raw wastewater) with bovine + PMMoV factor. From September 2021 onwards, the method was changed. Please see this page for the most recent data.
This project, led by associate professor Zeynep Cetecioglu Gurol and colleagues (KTH Royal Institute of Technology; zeynepcg@kth.se), is a collaboration between the SciLifeLab COVID-19 National Research Program and the SEED and Chemical Engineering departments at KTH, in close collaboration with Stockholm Vatten och Avfall and the Käppala Association.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Historic data for Örebro and Umeå</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/dashboards/wastewater/covid_quantification/historic_orebro_umea/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/dashboards/wastewater/covid_quantification/historic_orebro_umea/</guid>
      <description>This page displays data on the amount of SARS-CoV-2 in Umeå and Örebro wastewater between October 2020 and June 2021. After June 2021, a new method is used for analyses of wastewater, and the most recent data can be found here.
The data displayed here were collected as part of a research project led by associate professor Maja Malmberg (SLU, Swedish University of Agricultural Sciences; maja.malmberg@slu.se) in collaboration with the SciLifeLab COVID-19 National Research Program and associate professor Mette Myrmel at the Norwegian University of Life Sciences.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Imaging data</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/datasets/imaging/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/datasets/imaging/</guid>
      <description>Published Data General useful data sources Imaging data at the EMBL-EBI:
  BioImage Archive - stores and distributes biological images that are useful to life-science researchers currently in development. In its first phase, the BioImage Archive will provide archiving services to EMPIAR. Image data currently in BioStudies will also be migrated to the BioImage Archive, whilst new direct image-data submissions will be accepted by BioStudies, Cell-IDR or Tissue-IDR.
  Electron Microscopy Public Image Archive(EMPIAR) - public resource for raw electron microscopy images.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Infectious diseases</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/topics/infectious-diseases/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/topics/infectious-diseases/</guid>
      <description>Background Infectious diseases are one of the most prominent threats to public health globally. Multiple types of organisms cause infectious disease, including bacteria (for example, urinary tract infections, tuberculosis), viruses (for example, the common cold, influenza, and coronaviruses), fungi (for example, ringworm), and parasitic organisms (for example, malaria).
Infectious diseases can spread directly or indirectly in multiple different ways. For example, they may spread through droplets in the air, by exchanging bodily fluids, and by consuming contaminated food.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Influenza resources</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/topics/influenza/resources/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/topics/influenza/resources/</guid>
      <description>Resource or database connected to Influenza WHO Global Influenza Programme https://www.who.int/teams/global-influenza-programme
The Global Influenza Program (GIP) from the World Health Organisation (WHO) is providing its member states with strategic guidance eg. surveillance, monitoring and technical support. The GIP program collects and analyzes virological and epidemiological data from the member states which will allow WHO to monitor trends in influenza. WHO also supports selection of influenza strains for seasonal vaccines. The GIP is also working to support the members states with pandemic preparedness efforts such as seasonal, zoonotic, and pandemic influenza threats.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Metagenomic sequencing for pathogen identification and analysis</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/resources/metagenomic_seq_pathogens/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/resources/metagenomic_seq_pathogens/</guid>
      <description>Clinical Microbiology at Linköping University Hospital plans to develop a capability to quickly identify and characterize unknown pathogens through metagenomic sequencing. This will enable detection and sequence analysis of pathogens directly from clinical samples of unknown etiology, without the need of pathogen-specific reagents.
Since the middle of June, an M.Sc. in engineering biology has been recruited for the project and is currently learning the already developed methods for whole-genome sequencing of bacteria and target enrichment sequencing of SARS-CoV-2, with supervision from a biologist and a bioinformatician involved in the project.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Monitoring the Swedish population-level neutralization of current and emerging SARS-CoV-2 variants (SwedN)</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/resources/swedn/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/resources/swedn/</guid>
      <description>From an overwhelming array of evidence from clinical trials, observational studies, and animal models, the most reliable correlate of protection from SARS-CoV-2 infection, and from severe disease, is neutralizing antibody potency. With potent neutralizing antibodies against a circulating SARS-CoV-2 variant, the individual is less likely to be infected and less likely to develop severe disease if infected.
While large amounts of money are spent on virus sequencing to monitor circulating SARS-CoV-2 variants, it is difficult to convert this “variant prevalence” information into an assessment of risk without knowing the distribution of antibody responses against these circulating variants.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mpox</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/topics/mpox/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/topics/mpox/</guid>
      <description>This page is under development, with more resources being added shortly. In the meantime, check out the mpox page in our &#39;emerging pathogens&#39; section. That page contains more extensive information and useful links to other related resources.  Background Mpox a.k.a. Monkeypox is caused by the mpox virus, and is a zoonotic disease (i.e. it is transmitted from animals to humans). The mpox virus is a member of the Orthopoxvirus genus in the family Poxviridae.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mpox: ongoing research, data, publications and preprints</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/pathogens/mpox/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/pathogens/mpox/</guid>
      <description>General information Mpox a.k.a. Monkeypox is a zoonotic disease (i.e. one that is transmitted from animals to humans) caused by the mpox virus. The virus is a member of the Orthopoxvirus genus in the family Poxviridae. There are currently two clades of mpox virus: the West African clade and the Congo Basin (Central African) clade according to WHO. It is closely related to the virus that causes smallpox (variola virus), which has had a major negative impact on human populations throughout history.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Multiplex and high-throughput multi-disease serology</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/resources/serology/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/resources/serology/</guid>
      <description>High-throughput serology analysis is an important tool for evaluating the serostatus and potential immunity of the population. The information provided can both monitor the spread of a disease and aid in making informed decisions regarding efficient societal restrictions and vaccination strategies. A critical concern for performing high-throughput serology, especially during a pandemic, is continuous access to the required reagents.
During spring 2020, a highly performing, high-throughput and multiplex SARS-CoV-2 serology assay was in short time developed by a multidisciplinary team from KTH and SciLifeLab, also involving multiple actors within public, commercial, and healthcare sectors.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>National Health Metadata Repository - RUT</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/data_types/health_data/rut/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/data_types/health_data/rut/</guid>
      <description>The Swedish Research Council has set up a single national entry point, RegisterResearch.se, which provides information and support on register-based research in Sweden. Rich metadata descriptions from public authority register, national quality registers and biobank sample collections can be found via the digital infrastructure and metadata platform RUT (Register Utiliser Tool). RUT currently includes metadata with COVID-19 variables from the National Quality Register for intensive care (SIR). Addition of COVID-19 variables to registers is currently taking place.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>National Pandemic Centre SARS-CoV-2 (COVID-19) test statistics</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/dashboards/npc-statistics/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/dashboards/npc-statistics/</guid>
      <description>The National Pandemic Centre (NPC) at Karolinska Institute ceased operations of high throughput PCR diagnostics on 2020-12-21.
The data presented here is no longer updated but is kept for historical reference.
KI Press Release  The dataset visualised in the graphs on this page is available here. The numbers reported here were compiled automatically and, as such, might not correspond to the numbers reported through other sources for different reasons.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Next generation clinical virology</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/resources/ng_clinical_virology/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/resources/ng_clinical_virology/</guid>
      <description>Next generation sequencing offers numerous possibilities for improved diagnostics and management of infectious diseases. A comprehensive goal for Clinical Microbiology at Karolinska is to apply viral metagenomics and human immune transcriptomics in healthcare, and develop the following capabilities:
 Diagnostic metagenomic sequencing. Metagenomic virus surveillance of respiratory samples. Characterization of unclassifiable metagenomic sequences. Host immune transcriptome based microbial diagnostics. Immunotherapy guidance.  Activities so far have focused on establishing diagnostic metagenomic sequencing with a focus on viral infections.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Omicron variant of concern: ongoing research, data, publications and preprints</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/pathogens/voc/omicron/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/pathogens/voc/omicron/</guid>
      <description>Variants of Concern (VOC)  Omicron
    February 2022: We have stopped tracking updates related to Omicron VoC. This page will stay available as an archive. NB: Some sections on this page that fetch automatically information from other sections of the Portal will continue to update.  On this page we have compiled current knowledge on Omicron, the latest SARS-CoV-2 variant to be designated as a Variant of Concern (VOC).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Other data</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/datasets/other/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/datasets/other/</guid>
      <description>Published Data Information about available data of the types that do not fit into other categories of data on our portal is displayed on this page.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Other National Portals</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/partners/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/partners/</guid>
      <description>The Swedish Pathogens Portal originated as the &amp;lsquo;Swedish COVID-19 Data Portal&amp;rsquo;. It was the first national node of the European COVID-19 Data Platform; a Europe-wide platform allowing researchers to upload, access, and analyse COVID-19 related datasets. The European COVID-19 Data Platform was launched in the spring of 2020 when the European Commission took the initiative to develop a European data sharing platform for COVID-19 research efforts. It is operated by the European Molecular Biology Laboratory - European Bioinformatics Institute (EMBL-EBI) and partners.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Pandemic Laboratory Preparedness (PLP) program</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/plp-program-background/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/plp-program-background/</guid>
      <description>The Science for Life Laboratory (SciLifeLab) research community has been actively engaged in national and international COVID-19 research efforts from very early in the pandemic. The ability to access established SciLifeLab infrastructure and expertise within that research community undoubtedly expedited studies on COVID-19/SARS-CoV-2 at the molecular, cellular, patient, population, and environmental levels.
As part of their efforts to tackle the pandemic, SciLifeLab was also quick to establish programs to support research efforts.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Pandemic preparedness against antimicrobial resistance through wastewater monitoring</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/resources/amr_wastewater/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/resources/amr_wastewater/</guid>
      <description>The increasing spread of antimicrobial resistance (AMR) is a serious threat to human and animal health, and a OneHealth approach is needed to reduce the transmission of AMR microorganisms. AMR monitoring is considered essential to assess: (i) the overall AR status in a human population or community; (ii) the risks that AMR evolves and spread across One-Health compartments; (iii) the risk of AMR transmission to humans. The difficulties in global monitoring of AMR are many; ranging from ethical issues regarding human samples to lack of comparable methods available across nations.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Pandemic sample centers - enabling SciLifeLab infrastructures to form pandemic preparedness capability</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/resources/sample-center/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/resources/sample-center/</guid>
      <description>In order to allow the molecular analysis of emerging biological threats, early access to biological samples is warranted. During the early stages of the COVID-19 pandemic, progress was limited by a lack of relevant clinical samples. This project aims to create a unit, early pandemic sample center, that allows rapid handling of biological specimens and facilitates connections between SciLifeLab facilities and university hospitals. Karolinska and Uppsala University Hospitals will be used in trials to test the proposed model.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Partner organisations</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/about/partner_organisations/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/about/partner_organisations/</guid>
      <description>Pathogens Portal The Pathogens Portal, maintained by the European Molecular Biology Laboratory&#39;s European Bioinformatics Institute (EMBL-EBI) and partners, was launched in July 2023. The Pathogens Portal is a resource for e.g. researchers, clinicians, and policymakers. Its aim is to facilitate access to the latest and most comprehensive datasets on pathogens. The COVID-19 pandemic put a spotlight on the importance of data sharing and for focused access to relevant datasets.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Post COVID-19 condition in Sweden: statistics, research projects, and available data</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/dashboards/post_covid/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/dashboards/post_covid/</guid>
      <description>Since the beginning of 2020, the COVID-19 pandemic has challenged healthcare and dramatically changed daily life for people worldwide. The severity of symptoms experienced by patients during the acute infection phase of COVID-19 disease varies between individuals from mild to severe. After this phase, there are usually no indications that the disease will have any long-term effects on their health, regardless of the severity of symptoms experienced during the acute infection phase.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Pre-analytics for pandemic preparedness</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/resources/preanalytics/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/resources/preanalytics/</guid>
      <description>This project will focus on the crucial pre-analytical steps for detection of viruses and bacteria with metagenomics in order to deliver a national standard operating procedure. The main focus will be to compare and evaluate matrices for sample transportation, effect of storage and nucleic acid extraction methods. The main outcome measure will be the effect on the quality (quantity and fragmentation of DNA/cDNA, the amount of microbial reads, bias in relative composition and ability to use sequences for further typing) of fast long-read sequencing using Oxford Nanopore technology and bioinformatics tools.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Preparedness by early detection of infections in the elderly</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/resources/early_detection_elderly/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/resources/early_detection_elderly/</guid>
      <description>Susceptibility to viral or bacterial infections and risk for severe or fatal disease increases with age and development of comorbidities. Accordingly, half of all fatal covid-19 cases at the initial phase of the pandemic in Sweden’s population of 10 million occurred among approximately 80 000 people living in in nursing homes. Similarly, age over 65 is a significant risk factor for fatal influenza type A infection. Rapid, sensitive, and specific surveillance of respiratory infections and disease outcomes among people in nursing homes may provide information that can help early outbreak detection and to predict the epidemic or pandemic potential of new outbreaks.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Preparedness for tracking resistant and virulent bacterial and fungal pathogens (TRACK-PATH)</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/resources/track_path/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/resources/track_path/</guid>
      <description>The project consists of three parts:
 Characterization of microbial strains (bacteria and fungi) with resistance to recently introduced antimicrobials. Characterization of virulent pathogens causing unexpectedly severe infections. Exploring methods for studying host-pathogen interaction. During the first months of the project a bioinformatician has been recruited to work on transcriptomics and on establishing pipelines for characterization of virulent pathogens.  We have selected &amp;gt;40 isogenic mutants of Escherichia coli, Klebsiella pneumoniae, Pseudomonas aeruginosa, and Acinetobacter baumannii with resistance to at least one of the two novel antimicrobials cefiderocol and aztreonam-avibactam.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Present and past research projects on COVID-19</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/research_projects/all_covid_projects/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/research_projects/all_covid_projects/</guid>
      <description>This page lists all projects on COVID-19 and SARS-CoV-2 which are funded by major funding agencies in Sweden since the start of the COVID-19 pandemic that the Portal team tracked. The list includes both projects for which funding has expired and projects that are ongoing now.
See this page for a list of ongoing funded research projects relevant to pandemic preparedness.
 Last updated: 2023-03-06 
Funder AFA-försäkring  Formas  Forte  Hjärt-Lungfonden  Swedish Research Council  Swedish Research Council, Hjärt-Lungfonden, Swedish Foundation for Strategic Research  Swedish Social Insurance Agency  Vetenskapsrådet  Vinnova  VR  PI affiliation Dalarna University  Gothenburg University  Göteborgs universitet  Högskolan Kristianstad  IFAU, Institutet för arbetsmarknads- och utbildningspolitisk utvärdering  Karlstad University  Karolinska Institute  Karolinska Institutet  KTH, Kungliga tekniska högskolan  Linköping pingUniversity  Linköping University  Linköpings universitet  Lund University  Lunds universitet  Malmö universitet  Malmö University  Region Västmanland  Stockholm University  Stockholms universitet  Umeå University  University of Gothenburg  Uppsala universitet  Uppsala University  Örebro University    Project title Funder Topics      Mental health of young LGBTQ&amp;#43; people: Trends over time and during the COVID-19 pandemic, causes of mental ill-health, and ways to improve mental health of young LGBTQ&amp;#43; people Host institute: Karolinska Institute</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Privacy Policy</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/privacy/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/privacy/</guid>
      <description>SciLifeLab operates the pathogens.se and covid19dataportal websites (including its subdomains such as biobanks.covid19dataportal.se), which provides the SERVICE.
This page is used to inform website visitors regarding our personal data processing policy. If you choose to use our Service, then your personal data will be processed in accordance with this policy.
The Personal Information that we collect are used for providing and improving the Service. We will not use or share your information with anyone except as described in this Privacy Policy.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Programs and organisations behind the portal</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/about/organisations_and_programs/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/about/organisations_and_programs/</guid>
      <description>Pandemic Laboratory Preparedness (PLP) Program SciLifeLab (Science for Life Laboratory) was commissioned by the Swedish govenment to prepare resources and capabilities that can be used to deal with future pandemics. The assignment broadly involved supporting research related to infectious diseases (e.g. in diagnostics, analysis of infection, immunity, and the development of resistance to therapies in pathogens), and building competence and developing technologies related to pandemic research (e.g. in sequencing, genetic analysis, immunology, and big data).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Protein data</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/datasets/protein/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/datasets/protein/</guid>
      <description>Published Data General useful data sources   The Human Protein Atlas (HPA) provides open access to protein expression data across human organs, tissues and cells. This protein resource is organized into focused sections for tissue expression, subcellular expression, proteins in the brain or in blood, proteins related to pathology and metabolic pathways. A special page of HPA has been dedicated to human proteins and SARS-CoV-2.
  PRIDE PRoteomics IDEntifications (PRIDE) Archive database - centralized, standards compliant, public data repository for mass spectrometry proteomics data, including protein and peptide identifications and the corresponding expression values, post-translational modifications and supporting mass spectra evidence (both as raw data and peak list files).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Public health data</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/datasets/public-health/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/datasets/public-health/</guid>
      <description>Published Data General useful data sources  The COVID-19 Response Measures Database, compiled by the European Centre For Disease Prevention and Control (ECDC). The database is an archive of non-pharmaceutical interventions, or measures, introduced by 30 countries in the European Union and the European Economic Area in response to the coronavirus disease (COVID-19) pandemic, including the start and end date of each measure. The database is reviewed and updated every two weeks.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rapid discovery of neutralizing monoclonal antibodies for first line defense</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/resources/monoclonal_antibodies/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/resources/monoclonal_antibodies/</guid>
      <description>With the ongoing SARS-CoV-2 pandemic, there is a need to identify broadly neutralizing monoclonal antibodies (mAbs) that can be used as first-line defense against newly emerging variants. Already in the first year of the pandemic, the scientific community showed that highly effective neutralizing mAbs can be isolated from convalescent donors, some of which were rapidly approved for clinical use. Because of their exquisite specificities, monoclonal antibodies are generally safe and rarely give side effects.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rapid establishment of comprehensive laboratory pandemic preparedness – RAPID-SEQ</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/resources/rapid-seq/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/resources/rapid-seq/</guid>
      <description>The emergence of SARS-CoV-2 VOCs has shown the need for continuous large- scale surveillance to monitor for future pandemic threats. This project builds on established collaboration between SciLifeLab and the Karolinska University Laboratory, and provide samples, data and expertise from Sweden’s largest microbiology laboratory. In addition, the structure is part of Genomic Medicine Sweden (GMS) which is ensuring the coordination with other national efforts.
The laboratory has established large-scale WGS of SARS-CoV-2 (to-date 2000+ samples sequenced and reported to SMInet.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rapid typing of emerging variants in a clinical setting</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/resources/rapid_type_variants/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/resources/rapid_type_variants/</guid>
      <description>Throughout the recent SARS-CoV-2 pandemic, it has been evident that a swift response relies on the capacity to quickly establish methodologies for clinical diagnostics and epidemiologic surveillance. The first generation of commercial kits were sold as &amp;ldquo;Research Use Only&amp;rdquo;, had low capacity, and were often characterised by poor performance. Robust methodologies were, despite tremendous effort from the manufacturers and the frequent use of &amp;ldquo;Emergency Use&amp;rdquo; labelling by regulatory agencies, not available until the first wave was almost over.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Register-based COVID-19 vaccination study (RECOVAC)</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/dashboards/recovac/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/dashboards/recovac/</guid>
      <description>RECOVAC project overview The RECOVAC project (register-based large-scale national population study to monitor COVID-19 vaccination effectiveness and safety) is a register-based national population study focused on monitoring the effectiveness and safety of COVID-19 vaccinations. It is a subproject of SCIFI-PEARL (the Swedish COVID-19 Investigation for Future Insights – a Population Epidemiology Approach using Register Linkage). The RECOVAC project uses a multi-register observational research approach to track the effectiveness of COVID-19 vaccination research and vaccine safety in Sweden.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Register-based research: information, tools, examples</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/register-based-research/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/register-based-research/</guid>
      <description>The current pandemic has highlighted the importance of accelerating research in order to meet the global health challenge. Knowledge about COVID-19 has, over the last two years, rapidly increased through research studies, pre-clinical studies, clinical trials, and register-based studies using real-patient data.
Register-based data can contribute with important real-patient data aspects to research and add a new dimension to the field. Linking register-based data, clinical data, and biobank samples can give insights into not yet not elucidated parts of COVID-19 disease urgently warranted.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Resources</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/support_services/resources/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/support_services/resources/</guid>
      <description>Infrastructures COVID-19 HPC Consortium The consortium encompasses computing capabilities from some of the most powerful and advanced computers in the world. It is possible to request allocations of up to 6 months.
ELIXIR Computing Resources ELIXIR nodes have made available a broad variety of computing resources.
European Galaxy COVID-19 Project Publicly accessible infrastructure and workflows for SARS-CoV-2 data analyses from different scientific domains (genomics, proteomics, metabolomics, cheminformatics&amp;hellip;).
Partnership for Advanced Computing in Europe (PRACE) PRACE provides access to world-class high performance computing resources for researchers from academia and industry.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>SARS-CoV-2 bioinformatics pipeline – GMS Arctic</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/resources-subprojects/gms-arctic/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/resources-subprojects/gms-arctic/</guid>
      <description>A pipeline for bioinformatical analysis of SARS-CoV-2 data was developed within Genomics Medicine Sweden during the spring of 2021. The pipeline extends on the analysis developed by the international collaboration ArticNetwork and the COG-UK consortium. It is currently in clinical use across Sweden and is continually updated with the latest SARS-CoV-2 variants.
The pipeline performs typing of SARS-CoV-2 data using both the Pangolin and Nextstrain classification systems. In addition, it also runs quality control, variant calling and supplies a genome consensus sequence for each sample.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>SARS-CoV-2 Reporter for visualization of SARS-CoV-2 genome sequence data (SC2reporter)</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/resources-subprojects/sc2reporter/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/resources-subprojects/sc2reporter/</guid>
      <description>A web-based visualization application for the ongoing SARS-CoV-2 pandemic. The tool is primarily used for epidemiological analysis where pipeline analysis results and metadata are loaded into a mongoDB database. The SNVs and indels can then be compared between all isolated in the database.
For more information on the Pandemic Laboratory Preparedness resources associated with this subproject, see Genomic Pandemic Preparedness Portfolio (G3P). Please also refer to other associated subprojects; GMS Arctic and taxprofiler.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>SARS-CoV-2 variants detected in Region Uppsala</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/dashboards/variants_region_uppsala/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/dashboards/variants_region_uppsala/</guid>
      <description>Introduction Surveillance of a viral pathogen is essential for minimising the impacts of that pathogen on society. Without surveillance, it is difficult to understand whether a given pathogen occurs in the area, whether new strains have appeared, or if an outbreak may be likely.
Throughout the pandemic and until present day, the section for Clinical Microbiology and Hospital Hygiene at Uppsala University Hospital have conducted surveillance for SARS-CoV-2 in Uppsala. To do this, they performed whole genome sequencing on samples from SARS-CoV-2 positive patients in the Uppsala region.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>SciLifeLab Autoimmunity and Serology profiling facility SARS-CoV-2 antibody test statistics</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/dashboards/serology-statistics/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/dashboards/serology-statistics/</guid>
      <description>Graphs on this page are based on data as per  var xmlhttp = new XMLHttpRequest(); xmlhttp.onreadystatechange = function() { if (this.readyState == 4 &amp;&amp; this.status == 200) { var dataset_info = JSON.parse(this.responseText); document.getElementById(&#34;last_modified&#34;).innerText = String(dataset_info.modified).substring(0,10); } }; xmlhttp.open(&#34;GET&#34;, &#34;https://datagraphics.dc.scilifelab.se/api/dataset/6d6f551abc10413a97a6ab64ebac46bd&#34;, true); xmlhttp.send();  . Total serology test numbers The total number of tests run at SciLifeLab Autoimmunity and Serology profiling facility since the start, split into tests with a positive IgG-result, tests with a negative IgG-result, and R&amp;amp;D tests.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>SEEC: Swedish Environmental Epidemiology Center</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/resources/seec/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/resources/seec/</guid>
      <description>SEEC is a national capacity-building center that bridges the current gap between epidemiology and environmental assessment. It provides for rapid and effective response to detected pathogens as well as population level epidemiology. SEEC also stands for the standardization of molecular and experimental methods for continuous assessment of known and emerging pathogens of concern in Sweden.
Our aim is to provide:
 Continued and extended wastewater-based monitoring of the ongoing Covid-19 pandemic.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Serology data</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/datasets/serology/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/datasets/serology/</guid>
      <description>Published Data Data available from Swedish public agencies and large data produces  SciLifeLab Autoimmunity and Serology profiling facility SARS-CoV-2 antibody test statistics. Hosted by us, updated manually on a weekly basis.  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Services</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/data_types/compound_and_target_data/services/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/data_types/compound_and_target_data/services/</guid>
      <description>Small molecule screening and drug repurposing research Chemical Biology Consortium Sweden (CBCS) From the Compound Center at the facility for Chemical Biology (CBCS) you may access ~200 000 compounds. The collection comprises sets that are chemical diverse and suitable for target based or cell based phenotypic screens identifying new compounds modelling a pathway or a target. Also known drugs and tool compounds are available for screening and for drug repurposing projects.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Services</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/data_types/imaging_data/services/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/data_types/imaging_data/services/</guid>
      <description>Facilities which offer data generation services for imaging:
  ALM Advanced Light Microscopy facility give support with advanced fluorescence microscopy for nanoscale biological visualization using SIM, STED, STORM/PALM superresolution imaging. The facility also support single molecule spectroscopy measurement and analysis with fluorescence correlation spectroscopy (FCS), as well as combined with superresolution dynamical studies (STED-FCS). Moreover, light-sheet fluorescence microscopy support allow users to image live and/or optically cleared larger samples. Submit your application at the NMI (National Microscopy Infrastructure) project portal.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Services</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/data_types/protein_data/services/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/data_types/protein_data/services/</guid>
      <description>Protein analysis can be conducted using different types of methodologies and across different types of samples. A brief description of technologies using affinity proteomics or mass spectrometry is listed below:
Affinity-based protein detection   Multiplexed analysis of proteins in body fluids at Plasma Profiling
  Array-based analysis of antibodies and autoantibody repertoires at Autoimmunity Profiling
  Proximity-based assays for high-specificity protein analyses at Proximity Assay
  Single cell and multi-target analysis in blood at Mass Cytometry</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Services: genomics &amp; transcriptomics</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/data_types/genomics_transcriptomics/services/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/data_types/genomics_transcriptomics/services/</guid>
      <description>SciLifeLab Genomics Platform The SciLifeLab Genomics Platform has a number of different facilities offering services to researchers across a range of techniques.
Clinical Genomics Stockholm (Diagnostics Development) In collaboration with Clinical Microbiology department at Karolinska University Hospital, Clinical Genomics Stockholm facility provides sequencing of SARS-CoV-2 using the ARTIC protocol. As part of this collaboration we can provide access to BSL-3 laboratories, high capacity DNA extraction, amplicon sequencing and bioinformatic analylsis. We have capacity to handle projects with thousands of samples, or projects in need of services in prospective manner.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Share data</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/share-data/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/share-data/</guid>
      <description>Share data in a public repository Publish your infectious disease and pandemic preparedness data to make it available for the rest of the research community. The data should be deposited in a public repository together with descriptive metadata. For many biological datatypes, there are international databases that can be considered de facto standards.
The European Bioinformatics Institute (EBI) hosts many different international data repositories which should be used if appropriate. For data types where no suitable international repository is available, your data can be deposited to the SciLifeLab Data Repository which is run by the SciLifeLab Data Centre (submissions accepted from all life science researchers in Sweden).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Social science and humanities data</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/datasets/social-science-humanities/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/datasets/social-science-humanities/</guid>
      <description>Published Data General useful data sources   Consortium of European Social Science Data Archives (CESSDA) provides large-scale, integrates, and sustainable data services targetted at social science work. They bring together arcgives of social science data from across Europe. They promote social science findings, and support research and coorperation at both national and international levels.
  BY-COVID resource filtering CESSDA resources.
  Data available on the European COVID-19 Data Portal  Social science and humanities data from the CESSDA catalogue  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>State-of-the-art biosafety level 3 (BSL3) facility</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/resources-subprojects/bsl3-facility/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/resources-subprojects/bsl3-facility/</guid>
      <description>BSL3 Biomedicum is fully equipped with state-of-the-art equipment and expertise staff to perform a wide range of research with any BSL3 pathogens. Our facility offers unique applications for pathogen aerobiology and high-throughput screening and service-based projects for external users.
BSL3 Biomedicum is open for companies to perform their research with pathogenic viruses. As an example, Biomedrex is developing CRISPR-based antivirals at BSL3 Biomedicum.
For more information on the Pandemic Laboratory Preparedness resources associated with this subproject, see BSL3 Biomedicum-SciLifeLab Collaborative Platform and Swedish biosafety level 3 (BSL3) network.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Strengthening population health surveillance and epidemics monitoring by microsampling</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/resources/microsampling_monitor/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/resources/microsampling_monitor/</guid>
      <description>Minimally invasive biofluid collections through microsampling devices coupled with molecular analyses has shown the potential to enable large-scale population and epidemiological studies. Patient-centric sampling approach such as dried blood spots (DBS) could have a tremendous impact on the prevention and management of future pandemics facilitating monitoring of disease spread, virulence, incubation period, immunogenicity, impact of new variants and eventually resistance to therapy. Despite the increasing interest in implementing microsampling strategies in research, healthcare and pharma, the field still lacks widespread use of devices with robust and standardized protocols of analysis.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Swedish biosafety level 3 (BSL3) network</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/resources-subprojects/bsl3-network/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/resources-subprojects/bsl3-network/</guid>
      <description>High-level containment laboratories are a cornerstone for pandemic laboratory preparedness. The purpose of the Swedish BSL3 Network is to strengthen national pandemic laboratory preparedness by improving interactions between BSL3 facilities in the country.
For more information on the Pandemic Laboratory Preparedness resources associated with this subproject, see BSL3 Biomedicum-SciLifeLab Collaborative Platform and State-of-the-art biosafety level 3 (BSL3) facility.
Current members of the Swedish BSL3 network  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Systems-level immunomonitoring to unravel immune response to a novel pathogen</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/resources/immunomonitoring/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/resources/immunomonitoring/</guid>
      <description>Early research into SARS-CoV-2 immune responses and the how the immune responses varied among different patients, based on age, sex and prior health status in relation to COVID-19 disease outcome, has been of outmost importance for improved COVID-19 survival rates. The TBy unpacking the complex immune system pathways involved in sensing the SARS-CoV-2 virus, as well as the interference of the virus in antiviral IFN-I responses are examples of immunological findings based on patient-data.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Text and literature</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/support_services/text_and_literature/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/support_services/text_and_literature/</guid>
      <description>For central COVID-19 hubs of text and literature, please see:
 EuropePMC at the COVID-19 Data Portal BioRxiv and MedRxiv COVID-19 preprints  CDC COVID-19 Research Articles A downloadable database of COVID-19 literature. This database is updated by systematically searching various bibliographic databases and hand searching selected grey literature sources.
CORD-19 dataset Large collection of scientific articles (currently 128000) related to coronaviruses from Pubmed, biorxiv, medrxiv and other sources. All articles are provided in a standardized JSON format.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Administration and Study of COVID-19 Vaccines in Sweden</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/dashboards/vaccines/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/dashboards/vaccines/</guid>
      <description>The data on this page is no longer updated at the data source. We are currently assessing the use of other data sources for vaccine data. Please see our RECOVAC dashboard for information on vaccine effectiveness and safety.  General information on COVID-19 vaccines Over the last two years, the COVID-19 pandemic has challenged societies and healthcare systems worldwide. In response, vaccines and therapeautic treatments have been rapidly developed. To date (October 2022), the European Medicines Agency (EMA) has approved six vaccines against COVID-19:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tutorial for SARS-CoV-2 genome data submission to ENA</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/support_services/tutorial_ena/tutorial_ena_contact/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/support_services/tutorial_ena/tutorial_ena_contact/</guid>
      <description>Getting Further Support About the use of this tutorial/Brokering to ENA If you have any questions/comments regarding the tutorial itself, need general advice with submission, or would like the Swedish COVID Data Portal team to broker a submission, please contact us using this form or send an email to us at datacentre@scilifelab.se.
Whilst making a submission If you require specific support while making a submission, please contact ENA support.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tutorial for SARS-CoV-2 genome data submission to ENA</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/support_services/tutorial_ena/tutorial_ena_faqs/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/support_services/tutorial_ena/tutorial_ena_faqs/</guid>
      <description>Frequently Asked Questions (FAQs) Why should I submit sequences? The availability of sequence data has been vital for tracking the spread of variants, the identification of new variants, and understanding the relative risk to public health posed by different variants. If sequences had not been made available, it would have hindered efforts to fight the pandemic. Specifically, it would have been more difficult to develop effective policies to prevent the spread of the virus (e.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tutorial for SARS-CoV-2 genome data submission to ENA</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/support_services/tutorial_ena/tutorial_ena_intro/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/support_services/tutorial_ena/tutorial_ena_intro/</guid>
      <description>About this tutorial The research community has put considerable effort into research on the SARS-CoV-2 virus and COVID-19. Fast and open access to different data types (societal, molecular, epidemiological, among others) has been key to the swift development and deployment of, for example, preventative measures, tests, vaccines, and treatments for COVID-19. The pandemic has thus further highlighted how important making data open and FAIR (Findable, Accessible, Interoperable, Reusable) is in facilitating research efforts.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tutorial for SARS-CoV-2 genome data submission to ENA</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/support_services/tutorial_ena/tutorial_ena_selectsub/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/support_services/tutorial_ena/tutorial_ena_selectsub/</guid>
      <description>Introduction to submission routes and methods There are multiple ways to submit data and sequences into ENA. In order to do a submission of of &amp;lsquo;raw&amp;rsquo; sequences and/or assemblies, you need to use a combination of interactive interfaces in ENA, command-line based software, and APIs for scripts/custom software. The prospect of using multiple tools and determining which tools are better to use for a given part of a submission can seem daunting, especially if you are unfamiliar with the tools.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tutorial for SARS-CoV-2 genome data submission to ENA</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/support_services/tutorial_ena/tutorial_ena_subprep/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/support_services/tutorial_ena/tutorial_ena_subprep/</guid>
      <description>It is necessary to do some preparation of files before submission, regardless of the eventual submission route that you select. This page explains how to perform these initial steps, so that you can successfully complete your submission.
Required file formats All sequence files that are submitted to ENA must be in an appropriate file format to be accepted. Details of the formats are listed in the Terminology and Metadata tab. Once all the files are in order, you can start the submission process.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tutorial for SARS-CoV-2 genome data submission to ENA</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/support_services/tutorial_ena/tutorial_ena_subroute1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/support_services/tutorial_ena/tutorial_ena_subroute1/</guid>
      <description>When to use this route Route 1 is recommended for users with little to no experience using the command line, and for small scale (usually 1-10, but could be more) or infrequent submissions. It makes use of a combination of a web submission interface (Webin submission portal) and a command-line tool (Webin-CLI).
Data required for route 1 All of the data required to complete this submission can be downloaded together in a single zip file by clicking here.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tutorial for SARS-CoV-2 genome data submission to ENA</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/support_services/tutorial_ena/tutorial_ena_subroute2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/support_services/tutorial_ena/tutorial_ena_subroute2/</guid>
      <description>When to use this route Route 2 is recommended for those with advanced knowledge of using command line, and for those doing bulk submissions. It is the most suitable route for high-throughput, frequent submissions and automated systems. For this route, the metadata is typically provided to ENA in XML documents. This is true in all cases except for sequence assemblies, where the metadata is instead provided in JSON format. In either case, the metadata are submitted using cURL.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tutorial for SARS-CoV-2 genome data submission to ENA</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/support_services/tutorial_ena/tutorial_ena_terminology/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/support_services/tutorial_ena/tutorial_ena_terminology/</guid>
      <description>Definition of data types (as used in ENA)   &amp;lsquo;Raw&amp;rsquo; sequence data - Sequence data that is obtained directly from a sequencing instrument (e.g. in FASTA, FASTQ, BAM, or CRAM files). ENA recommends the use of FASTA/FASTQ file formats (described below), but accepts also other file formats.
  Analysed sequence data - Sequence data that has been processed in some way after being obtained from a sequencing instrument. Such data has been normalised, and perhaps also subject to other processing (e.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Visualisation of COVID-19 and SARS-CoV-2 research in Sweden as reflected in publications</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/dashboards/covid_publications/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/dashboards/covid_publications/</guid>
      <description>The visualisations on this page evaluate the development of COVID-19 and SARS-CoV-2 research across Sweden by assessing publication output. Specifically, we consider multiple aspects of journal publications and preprints where at least one author has an affiliation with a Swedish research institute. The database containing the publications themselves can be found on this page, and is available for download, please see DOI: 10.17044/scilifelab.14124014 for details. The database is manually curated, so may not be exhaustive.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ZSC: National core facility for Pandemic Preparedness</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/resources/zsc/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/resources/zsc/</guid>
      <description>1. Clinical study To understand the virus shedding and further the disease management for COVID-19 patients in intensive care unit (ICU), we have isolated SARS-CoV-2 from nasopharynx samples collected from COVID-19 patients admitted to ICU with severe respiratory failure at the Uppsala University Hospital, between December 2020 and June 2021. The resources are the clinical data from patients who were enrolled in the PronMed study.
2. Virome study The resources are samples and RNA-sequencing data from important zoonotic reservoirs: Swedish rodents and shrews, as well as mosquitoes and ticks.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
