<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Ongoing research projects on The Swedish Pathogens Portal</title>
    <link>https://www.pathogens.se/research_projects/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Ongoing research projects on The Swedish Pathogens Portal</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><atom:link href="https://www.pathogens.se/research_projects/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Present and past research projects on COVID-19</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/research_projects/all_covid_projects/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/research_projects/all_covid_projects/</guid>
      <description>This page lists all projects on COVID-19 and SARS-CoV-2 which are funded by major funding agencies in Sweden since the start of the COVID-19 pandemic that the Portal team tracked. The list includes both projects for which funding has expired and projects that are ongoing now.
See this page for a list of ongoing funded research projects relevant to pandemic preparedness.
 Last updated: 2023-03-06 
Funder AFA-försäkring  Formas  Forte  Hjärt-Lungfonden  Swedish Research Council  Swedish Research Council, Hjärt-Lungfonden, Swedish Foundation for Strategic Research  Swedish Social Insurance Agency  Vetenskapsrådet  Vinnova  VR  PI affiliation Dalarna University  Gothenburg University  Göteborgs universitet  Högskolan Kristianstad  IFAU, Institutet för arbetsmarknads- och utbildningspolitisk utvärdering  Karlstad University  Karolinska Institute  Karolinska Institutet  KTH, Kungliga tekniska högskolan  Linköping pingUniversity  Linköping University  Linköpings universitet  Lund University  Lunds universitet  Malmö universitet  Malmö University  Region Västmanland  Stockholm University  Stockholms universitet  Umeå University  University of Gothenburg  Uppsala universitet  Uppsala University  Örebro University    Project title Funder Topics      Mental health of young LGBTQ&amp;#43; people: Trends over time and during the COVID-19 pandemic, causes of mental ill-health, and ways to improve mental health of young LGBTQ&amp;#43; people Host institute: Karolinska Institute</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
