<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Portal news on The Swedish Pathogens Portal</title>
    <link>https://www.pathogens.se/updates/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Portal news on The Swedish Pathogens Portal</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 06 Nov 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.pathogens.se/updates/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>ISIDORe offers services for infectious disease research</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/updates/isidore_services/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Nov 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/updates/isidore_services/</guid>
      <description>The ISIDORe project aims to accelerate research and enhance pandemic preparedness efforts across Europe by assembling and providing access to crucial research resources. This includes their state-of-the-art facilities, services, advanced equipment, and expertise.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New dashboard showing SARS-CoV-2 sequences in Uppsala</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/updates/clinmicro_dashboard_launch/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Nov 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/updates/clinmicro_dashboard_launch/</guid>
      <description>Today we are launching a new dashboard showing information on the SARS-CoV-2 sequences detected during surveillance efforts by the section for Clinical Microbiology and Hospital Hygiene at Uppsala University Hospital.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Influenza added as a topic</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/updates/influenza_topic/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/updates/influenza_topic/</guid>
      <description>The content of the portal is broadly organised into &amp;lsquo;topics&amp;rsquo; related to pathogens and pandemic preparedness. Influenza is our latest topic.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New editorials section</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/updates/editorials/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/updates/editorials/</guid>
      <description>Today, we are launching a new section containing &amp;lsquo;editorials&amp;rsquo;. Editorials are short opinion-style articles detailing the &amp;lsquo;current thinking&amp;rsquo; on a given subject.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Becoming the first national node of the Pathogens Portal</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/updates/pathogens_portal/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Aug 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/updates/pathogens_portal/</guid>
      <description>We are very proud to announce that we are transitioning the Portal into the first national node of the Pathogens Portal. This marks the next step in our efforts related to pandemic preparedness.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Update to include data on enteric viruses in wastewater</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/updates/wastewater_enteric_viruses/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Aug 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/updates/wastewater_enteric_viruses/</guid>
      <description>The Portal is happy to announce that the wastewater dashboard now includes data on the quantification of enteric viruses from the Norder group at Gothenburg University (GU).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Recent updates and upcoming improvements</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/updates/updates_june_23/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Jun 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/updates/updates_june_23/</guid>
      <description>An overview of recent updates and improvements, and things to look out for in future.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>National COVID-19 biobank sample collection made available for research on the Portal</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/updates/npc_national_collection/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/updates/npc_national_collection/</guid>
      <description>A unique new sample collection has been added to the COVID-19 Sample Collection Database. The collection comprises of over 1.5 million samples collected by Swedish healthcare regions and processed by the National Pandemic Centre throughout the COVID-19 pandemic.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Swedish national resources on IDTk</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/updates/idtk_nation_resource/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/updates/idtk_nation_resource/</guid>
      <description>The Portal is a partner in the BY-COVID project. We have added a page to the Infectious Diseases Toolkit (IDTk) related to infectious disease data in Sweden.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Update to wastewater epidemiology dashboard</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/updates/update_wastewater_section/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/updates/update_wastewater_section/</guid>
      <description>The Portal team is working closely with groups at multiple Swedish universities that are involved in wastewater epidemiology to bring you the latest research in this area.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New section for pandemic preparedness events</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/updates/events_section/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/updates/events_section/</guid>
      <description>A new section has been added to promote events relevant to pandemic preparedness. This could include, for example, events related to biobanks, antibiotic resistance, or particular pathogens.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Portal welcomes editorial committee</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/updates/editorial_committee_23/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/updates/editorial_committee_23/</guid>
      <description>An editorial committee has now been established. The members will work closely with us to maximise the value of the Portal for the research community.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dashboard on Register-based COVID-19 Vaccination Study (RECOVAC) updated &amp; expanded</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/updates/recovac_update/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/updates/recovac_update/</guid>
      <description>New information related to determinants of vaccination and vaccine effectiveness have been added to the RECOVAC dashboard. The data has also been updated.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Explore COVID-19 publications in the field of social sciences and humanities on the Portal</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/updates/social_science_launch/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/updates/social_science_launch/</guid>
      <description>The Portal contains a database of COVID-19 publications involving Swedish researchers, and an available data section that shows which share data and/or code. It has long been possible to filter both the database and available databases by certain topics. Now, it is possible to identify the research, data, and code related to social sciences and humanities.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The latest updates to the COVID-19 &amp; Pandemic Preparedness Portal</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/updates/new_look/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/updates/new_look/</guid>
      <description>The scope of the portal has expanded in 2022 to include other pathogens and pandemic preparedness in general. We&amp;rsquo;ve created lots of new content and features in response to this (with more planned!).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Relaunch as Swedish COVID-19 and Pandemic Preparedness Portal</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/updates/pandemic_preparedness_transition/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/updates/pandemic_preparedness_transition/</guid>
      <description>Today we officially relaunch the site as the Swedish COVID-19 and Pandemic Preparedness Portal. We have been gradually transitioning sections of the Portal throughout 2022. Our latest section involves a collation of resources related to pandemic preparedness.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Section on Register-based COVID-19 Vaccination Study (RECOVAC) launched</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/updates/recovac/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/updates/recovac/</guid>
      <description>Data visualisations, information, and publications related to the RECOVAC project are now available on the portal. Visualisation codes are publicly available.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Swedish COVID-19 Data Portal two year anniversary</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/updates/second_year/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/updates/second_year/</guid>
      <description>The national Swedish COVID-19 Data Portal was launched two years ago today. The portal has been an important part of the pandemic response in Sweden. On our anniversary, we reflect on past highlights and look to the future.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tutorial for SARS-CoV-2 genome data submission to ENA now available</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/updates/ena_tutorial/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/updates/ena_tutorial/</guid>
      <description>Today, we are launching a ENA tutorial on how to submit SARS-CoV2 sequences to the European Nucleotide Archive. The tutorial caters to both experienced and first time sequence submitters.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Statistics, information, and research related to COVID-19 Vaccination in Sweden now available on the Portal</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/updates/vaccines_page/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/updates/vaccines_page/</guid>
      <description>The Visualizations are based on data freely available from the Swedish Health Agency (Folkhälsomyndigheten).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>BY-COVID – a collaborative effort to tackle data challenges that can hinder effective pandemic response</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/updates/by-covid/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/updates/by-covid/</guid>
      <description>The BeYond-COVID (BY-COVID) is a recently launched €12 million project funded by Horizon Europe. The Swedish COVID-19 Data Portal is one of the 53 partners from 19 countries taking part in the project.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New section on the Portal about register-based research</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/updates/section_register_based_research/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/updates/section_register_based_research/</guid>
      <description>The Swedish COVID-19 Data Portal is launching &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.pathogens.se/data_types/health_data/register_based_research/&#34;&gt;a section on register-based research in Sweden&lt;/a&gt; containing an overview of relevant registers and examples of research projects have used register data.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Statistics, information, and research about Post COVID-19 condition in Sweden now available on the Portal</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/updates/postcovid_launch/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/updates/postcovid_launch/</guid>
      <description>Today, for the first time, the Portal provides information and summary statistics to show the impact of ‘Post COVID-19 condition’ (‘Postcovid’ in Swedish) in Sweden, and the research underway. All data and code used on the page is publicly available.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Swedish SARS-CoV-2 and COVID-19 research output since the beginning of the pandemic</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/updates/covid_publications/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/updates/covid_publications/</guid>
      <description>To date, 1.400+ journal articles and preprints have been published by researchers affiliated to a Swedish university or research institute. The database of these publications is compiled by the Portal and is available for download.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Swedish COVID-19 Data Portal one year on - focus on openly sharing data and code</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/updates/first_year/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/updates/first_year/</guid>
      <description>One year ago today, on June 3rd 2020, the Swedish COVID-19 Data Portal was launched and became the first national node of the European data sharing platform for COVID-19 research efforts. Here, we look back at the highlights over the last year.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>SARS-CoV-2 wastewater data from cities across Sweden now available</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/updates/wastewater-data/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/updates/wastewater-data/</guid>
      <description>The Swedish COVID-19 Data Portal is launching &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.pathogens.se/data_types/environment/wastewater/&#34;&gt;a section with wastewater epidemiology data&lt;/a&gt;. Weekly data from Uppsala, Stockholm, Umeå, and Örebro is presented in graphs and available for download.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Database of COVID-19 sample collections and biobanks in Sweden launched</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/updates/sample_collection_database/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/updates/sample_collection_database/</guid>
      <description>In collaboration with Biobank Sweden, today we are launching a new section of the portal: the &lt;a href=&#34;https://biobanks.covid19dataportal.se/&#34;&gt;Swedish COVID-19 Sample Collection Database&lt;/a&gt;. The database allows to search for available biobank sample collections.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Data on COVID-19 testing in Uppsala County and dashboard with maps, trends and more now available</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/updates/crush_covid/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/updates/crush_covid/</guid>
      <description>The data portal is now launching &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.pathogens.se/data_types/health_data/crush_covid/&#34;&gt;a page with the CRUSH Covid dashboard&lt;/a&gt; with an option to download data on COVID-19 testing in each postal code of Uppsala County.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Statistics on SARS-CoV-2 antibody tests carried out by SciLifeLab now available</title>
      <link>https://www.pathogens.se/updates/serology_testing_stats/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pathogens.se/updates/serology_testing_stats/</guid>
      <description>We are launching a page with statistics on the SARS-CoV-2 antibody tests carried out at the SciLifeLab Autoimmunity and Serology profiling facility.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
